Guide to the Arlie R. Slabaugh Collection of Direct Mail Literature, 1914-1955 and undated RL.01201
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Arlie R. Slabaugh collection of direct mail literature
1914-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Slabaugh, Arlie R.
RL.01201
3 Linear Feet 464 items
Arlie R. Slabaugh was a publisher, hobby shop dealer and mail order promoter, and collector of periodicals related to the mail order business. The collection offers an overview of the mail order industry during pre-war and World War II-era in the United States. It is believed to have been created by Arlie R. Slabaugh, who was primarily a collector of coins and paper money, as well as a mail order promoter. The collection contains periodicals, amateur newspapers, hobby catalogs and printed ephemera, primarily from the 1930s-1940s, but also including examples from the 1920s and 1950s. Most are monthly periodicals, published as staple-bound or self-folding newsprint or glossy pamphlets, with some illustrations. Many of the items are regional in scope, possibly originating from major printing centers and distributed to local markets, particularly in the U.S. South, the Midwest and California.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, access to some materials is limited to preservation use copies available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Arlie R. Slabaugh Collection of Direct Mail Literature were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2007 and 2014.
Biographical Note
Arlie R. Slabaugh of Oakland, Maryland, and Virginia, was born in 1925. He worked as a publisher, hobby shop dealer and mail order promoter. He was also a numismatic historian, an expert on Confederate States paper money, monies and medals from prisoners of war, and Japanese invasion money and wrote a book entitled Confederate States Paper Money, first published in 1961 by Whitman Publishing Company. During the 1930s and 1940s, he also published his own collector magazine, Hobby Spotlite.
Chronology
1925 Born
1941 Joined the American Numismatic Association (ANA)
1954 Appointed the Associate Editor of Numismatic Scrapbook Magazine
1967 Began work for Franklin Mint
1981 Won the Numismatic Literary Guild Clemy Award
1989 Won the Krause Publications Ambassador Award
1991 Won the ANA's Medal of Merit
1997 Won the ANA's President's Award
2004 Won the ANA's Lifetime Achievement Award
2007 Died in Springfield, Pa.
Collection Overview
The collection offers an overview of the mail order industry during pre-war and World War II-era in the United States. It is believed to have been created by Arlie R. Slabaugh, who was primarily a collector of coins and paper money, as well as a mail order promoter. The collection contains periodicals, amateur newspapers, hobby catalogs and printed ephemera, primarily from the 1930s-1940s, but also including examples from the 1920s and 1950s. Most are monthly periodicals, published as staple-bound or self-folding newsprint or glossy pamphlets, with some illustrations. Many of the items are regional in scope, possibly originating from major printing centers and distributed to local markets, particularly in the U.S. South, the Midwest and California.
Restrictions on Access: Original newsprint items in oversize box are closed to researchers. Use copies are available in the collection.
Collection Arrangement
Items are arranged alphabetically by title into two series. The Pamphlets and Catalogs series contains printed materials and preservation use copies of original newsprint items, arranged alphabetically by title. The Oversize Originals series includes items in newspaper format that were separated into a restricted access oversize box for protection; copies of these items were filed among the open-use portion of the collection.
Related Material
Related materials can be found in the J. Walter Thompson Company collections of: Marketing Vertical Files; and the Ted Wilson Papers. Other materials can be found in the American Association of Advertising Agencies Records the Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly Catalog Collection; and the Sears, Roebuck and Company Catalog Collection.
Pamphlets -- United States -- 20th century; Mail-order business -- United States -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Ephemera; Target marketing -- United States; Hobbies -- United States -- History; Hobbies -- Periodicals; Mail-order business -- United States -- History; Mail-order business -- United States; Commercial catalogs; Direct marketing; Mail order catalogs; Slabaugh, Arlie R.; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Slabaugh, Arlie R.
- Pamphlets and Catalogs, 1914-1955 and undated, 5 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains periodicals, amateur newspapers, catalogs, handbills, coupons and other printed ephemera, primarily from the 1930s-40s, but also including examples from the 1920s and 1950s. Most are monthly periodicals, published as staple-bound or self-folding newsprint or glossy pamphlets, with some illustrations. Pencil notations appear in some items. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - ACME: Information Budget and Business Aid. Gordonsville, Va.: Square Deal Press, undated (Box 1)
  - Ad-Guide. Chicago, Ill.: Chicago Union Advertising Agency, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Ad-Lines. Indianapolis, Ind.: Ad-Man Press, Jan.-Feb. 1932 (Box 1)
  - Advertiser 8, no. 3 (1938) (Box 1)
  - Advertisers' Mail Order Bulletin 1, nos. 9, 10 (undated) (Box 1)
  - Advertisers' Press 2, no. 37 (1941) (Preservation use copy) (Box 1)
  - Arrival 3, no. 8 (undated). Pasadena, Calif.: Association of American Writers (Box 1)
  - Austin Advertiser. Cambridge, Mass.: Henry Stone, Aug. 1941 (Box 1)
  - Associated Syndicate Newspapers. Detroit, Mich.: Midwest Publications, 1941-1942 (Preservation use copy) (Box 1)
    [Includes vol. 1, no. 12; vol. 2, no. 4]
  - Bell's Gold Nuggets. Marysville, Calif.: Luther C. Bell, undated (Box 1)
  - Blake's Advertiser. Burlington, Iowa: G. Blake Company, Sept. 1941 (Box 1)
  - Burdge Press 5, no. 5 (1954). Camden, N.J.: J. Milton Burdge (Box 1)
  - California Advertiser. San Francisco, Calif.: California Advertiser, Apr. 1930 (Box 1)
  - Central Mail Advertiser. Oakland, Md.: Arlie Slabaugh, Aug. 1941-Mar. 1945 (Box 1)
  - Clarion. St. Louis, Mo.: Standard Press, Sept. 1937 (Box 1)
  - Consolidated Money Making Opportunities 2, no. 9 (1932). Mobile, Ala.: Elyod Publishing Company (Box 1)
  - Co-operative Ad-Circulator 163 (1942)(Preservation use copy) (Box 1)
  - Co-operative Market, Aug. 1941 (Box 1)
  - Daily Dollar. Chicago, Ill.: Arthur Sizemore, undated (Box 1)
  - Direct Mail Success. Dallas, Tex., 1941-1945. (Box 1)
    [Includes vol. 2, no. 8; vol. 3, nos. 9-10, 12; vol. 4, no. 5]
  - Dollar Fax 3, no. 1 (1940) (Box 1)
  - Emergency Money Collector 2, nos. 2-3 (1953) (Box 1)
  - Empire Mail Trade News 2-7 (undated). Gloucester City, N.J.: Mail Mart (Box 1)
  - Evers Earner 10, nos. 1-2 (1938). Elmhurst, N.Y., Harry Evers (Box 1)
  - Exchange 8, no. 1 (1942) (Box 1)
  - Good News 1, no. 7 (1941) (Box 1)
  - Guide to Good Reading, 1941-1952 (Box 1)
  - Hobby Humor 1, nos. 1-4 (1943-1944). New York, N.Y.: American Publishers (Box 1)
  - Hobby Spotlite 2-3 (1942-1943). Oakland, Md.: Spotlite Publications (Box 1)
  - Home Industries. Omaha, Neb.: C. C. Melota, 1934-1938 (Box 1)
    [Includes vol. 2, no. 7; vol. 6, no. 1]
  - Home Worker 9-40. Chicago, Ill.: Arthur Sizemore, undated (Box 1)
  - Home Worker 41-67. Chicago, Ill.: Arthur Sizemore, undated (Box 2)
  - Hutter's Advertiser. New York, N.Y.: William Hutter, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
    [Includes vol. 1, nos. 9-10; vol. 2, no. 2]
  - I Want to Buy. River Forest, Ill.: Forest Print Shop, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Income Increaser. Boston, Mass.: George W. Bucknam, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Increasing Sales by Mail. Edited by William C. Summers. Progressive Publications, undated (Box 2)
  - Independent Salesman 6, no. 10 (1929); 12, no. 9 (1935); 16, no. 8 (1939). Cincinnati, Ohio: Independent Salesman (Box 2)
  - Inner Circle: Behind the Scenes in the Mail Order Field. Atchison, Kan.: Mark Warden, undated (Box 2)
  - Keystone Mail Service 2, no. 1 (1934) (Box 2)
  - Lady Guide 1, nos. 3, 8 (1941) (Box 2)
  - Latest Moneymakers 2, nos. 10-11 (undated). Seattle, Wash.: C. A. Bryant (Box 2)
  - Liberty Mail Order Digest 3, no. 5 (1932) (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Advertiser 4, no. 11 (1934) (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Business 5 (1935) (Preservation use copy) (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Chat, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
    [Includes vol. 1, no. 7; vol. 2, no. 7]
  - Mail Order Digest Syndicate 59-73 (undated) (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Field 2, no. 11 (1927). Holton, Kan.: The Gossip Printery (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Iconoclast 12-22 (undated). Little Rock, Ark.: Associated Commission Mailers (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Ideas 1, no. 1 (1932) (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Journal, Sep. 1942-Dec. 1943. Edited by Nicholas De Vore (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Man 1-6 (1941-1942). Chicago, Ill.: Illinois Association of Mail Order Men (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Man's Timely Tips 3-14 (1931-1942). Paulding, Ohio: O.E. Brune (Box 2)
  - Mail Order Men's News 8, no. 3 (1937). Oyster Bay, N.Y.: Mail Order Men's Service (Box 3)
  - Mail Order News, 10, no. 10 (1914); 21, no. 3 (1924); 22, no. 3 (1925); and undated (Box 3)
  - Mail Order Opportunities Magazine. Parkersburg, W. Va.: Herbert R. Gant, 1942 (Box 3)
    [Includes vol. 2, nos. 3-4]
  - Mail Order Salesman 1, no. 3 (1937) (Box 3)
  - Mail Order Selling: Trade Journal of the Mail Order Business. Chicago, Ill.: Lind Publishing Company, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Mail Order Selling: The Modern American Salesman, 1928-1933 (Box 3)
    [Includes vol. 7, no. 6; vol. 12, no. 3; vol. 13, nos. 1-2]
  - Mail Order Speculator 5, no. 6 (1935). Chicago, Ill.: Sliss Speculations (Box 3)
  - Mail Order Success: A Magazine for the Circular Mailer 8, nos. 6, 8, 10, 11 (1934) (Box 3)
  - Mail Order Success: A Monthly Publication for the Mail Order Trade 5, no. 8 (1934). Pirates Cove, Fla.: Thomas MacPherson (Box 3)
  - Mail Order World, 1944, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Mail Sale Advertiser 7-23 (1941-1953). Jefferson City, Mo.: Dixon Advertising Agency [cont. next tite] (Box 3)
  - Mail Sale Advertiser 25 no.6 (1955). Chicago, Ill.: J.P. Brass (Box 3)
  - Mail Trade 2 (1941). Waterbury, Conn.: James Ives (Box 3)
  - Mail Trade Mimeos, Aug. 1941 (Box 3)
  - Mailindustries 1 (1941). Vicksburg, Miss.: Mailtrade Company (Box 3)
  - Marketing by Mail 10, no. 3 (1939). Jackson Heights, N.Y.: Darion System (Box 3)
  - Midget Collector 1, no. 2 (1921). Swayzee, Ind.: Gale Zirkle (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous circulars, 1934 and undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous leaflets, handbills and coupons, ca. 1940s-1950s (Box 3)
  - Money-Making Ideas 4 (1934) (Preservation use copy) (Box 3)
  - Money by Mail 19 (undated). Vancouver, B.C.: Pacific Advertising Service (Box 3)
  - Money by Mail 21-30 (undated). Somerville, N.J.: Blackstone Press (Box 3)
  - Monthly Confidential Bulletin 3 (undated). Little Rock, Ark.: Associated Commision Mailers (Box 3)
  - National Mail Order Advertising and Selling, 1941-1943 (Box 3)
  - National Opportunity 110-111 (undated) (Box 3)
  - New Times 1, no. 2 (1937). New York, N.Y.: New Times Company (Box 3)
  - Opportunity Dollars Work Book 8, no. 1 (1940). Burlington, Kan.: James R. Varvel (Box 3)
  - Opportunity Seekers Manual: Big Profit Moneymakers. Portland, Or.: Bagley Publications, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Palmer's Magazinette. Chicago, Ill.: Palmer's Publications, 1939, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Partners, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
    [Includes vol. 5, no. 7; vol. 7, no. 11]
  - Philatelic Mail. Chicago, Ill.: Charles Palmer & Son, 1941, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Popular Advertiser. Buffalo, Minn.: Bison Research Service, 1941, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Productive Postage. Gettysburg, Pa.: Battlefield Press, 1933-1937 (Box 4)
  - Profitable News 2, no. 11 (1938) (Box 4)
  - Profits 2, no. 3 (1934). Laurel, Md.: Patuxent Press (Box 4)
  - Profits from Classified Advertising, undated (Box 4)
  - Progressive Mail Trade, 1941-1946, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Prosperity Magazine 10, nos. 7-10 (1939). Chicago, Ill.: Arthur Sizemore (Box 4)
  - Publicity. New York, N.Y.: Samuel K. Gibbs, Nov. 1937 (Box 4)
  - Reliable Circular Mailer's Bulletin, 1933-1934 (Box 4)
  - Relics: The Magazine for Hobbyists. Sacramento, Calif.: P. Smith, Sr., May-Dec. 1945 (Box 4)
  - Roadman's Guide 23, no. 4. Yakima, Wash: Prof. J. Howard West (Box 4)
  - Roadman's Guide. J. C. Burrow, undated (Box 4)
  - Rural Printer. Hampton, Va.: Rural Print Shop, 1938-1942 (Box 4)
    [Includes vol. 15, 19-20]
  - Sales Opportunities 1, no. 5 (1935). Albert Lea, Minn.: George Hopkins (Box 5)
  - Schemer. Alliance, Ohio: Lewis Patterson, 1914, 1920, 1932-1951 (Box 5)
  - Shop Bulletin 1, nos. 1-6 (1946). Romney, W. Va.: Printing Shop (Box 5)
  - Spare Time Industries, Feb. 1938 (Box 5)
  - Spare Time Selling Magazine, Sept.-Oct. 1932 (Box 5)
  - Spring Magazine Bargains, 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - Something Different 33, no. 5 (1937). South Whitley, Ind.: Stump Printing Company (Box 5)
  - Southwestern Mail Order Journal 2, no. 1 (1942). Denton, Tex.: Southwestern Publishing Agency (Box 5)
  - Success Advertiser. Cleveland, Ohio: Art Publishing Company, 1934 and undated (Box 5)
  - Swapper's Friend: Dealer Edition 9-10 (1938-1939) (Box 5)
  - Swapper's Friend, 12, no. 12 (1931); 13, no. 7 (1932) (Box 5)
  - Three M Service. Argyle, Wis.: undated (Box 5)
  - Tidewater Advertiser. Hampton, Va.: E. C. Wood, 1942-1943 (Box 5)
    [Includes June, July 1942; Jan. 1943]
  - Tip Top Salesman 25-27 (1951-1952) (Box 5)
  - Universal Times 4, no. 11 (1942). Chelsea, Mass.: Royal Advertising Service (Box 5)
  - Western Advertiser. San Francisco, Calif.: Mail Order Studio, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Winner Mail Order Digest 4, no. 3 (1933). New York, N.Y.: John H. Winn (Box 5)
- Oversize Originals, 1934-1942 [Restricted], 1 boxes
  This series contains original amateur newspapers removed from previous boxes. Accewss is restricted to Use Copies available in previous series.
  - Advertisers' Press 2, no. 37 (1941) (Box 6)
  - Associated Syndicate Newspapers. Detroit, Mich.: Midwest Publications, 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Co-operative Ad-Circulator 163 (1942) (Box 6)
  - Mail Order Business 5 (1935) (Box 6)
  - Money-Making Ideas 4 (1934) (Box 6)